Register of the Edouard Jean Réquin Papers, 1915-1940
Hoover Institution Archives
Edouard Jean Réquin Papers,
1915-1940
XX294
Réquin, Edouard Jean, 1879-1953
4 manuscript boxes (1.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, military orders, memoranda, and writings, relating to Allied military operations in World War I, particularly Franco-American military cooperation; to proposals for a treaty of mutual assistance under auspices of the League of Nations, 1922-1923; and to operations of the French 4e Armee, 1940 May-June
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
France. Armée--Officers; France. Armée. Armée, 4e; League of Nations; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918--France; World War, 1914-1918--United States; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--France; France; United States--Armed Forces
Biographical Note
1879 Born
1900-1911 Member of expedition to North Africa
1916-1918 Member, General Staff of Marshals Joffre and Foch
1917-1918 Member, French Military Delegation to Washington
1919 Author, La Course de l'Amérique à la Victoire Technical Counsellor at Versailles Peace Conference
1924 Author, Projet de Traité d'Assistance Mutuelle
1930 French Military Representative at the League of Nations
1930-1932 Chief of Cabinet of Ministry of War
1938 Member, Supreme Council of War
1939-1940 Commander, 4th French Army
1941 Retired
1945 President, Société de la Légion d'Honneur
1946 "Président des anciens officiers de liaison près l'armée américaine" Author, Combats pour l'Honneur Author, Archinard et le Soudan
1949 Author, D'une guerre à l'autre 1919-1939. Souvenirs
1953 Died
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1918. (Box 1.)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- Speeches and Writings, 1918-1940. (Box 1-2.)
  Typewritten manuscripts of writings arranged alphabetically by title.
- Subject File, 1915-1940. (Box 3-4.)
  Correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, arranged alphabetically by topic.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1918
  - Gompers, Samuel, 1918 (Box 1.)
  - Harbord, General, 1918
- Speeches and Writings, 1918-1940
  - "La IVe Armée en Lorraine. Attaque allemande des 12-13 et 14 mai 1940" (The 4th Army in Lorraine. German attack of May 12-13 and 14, 1940), 1940., One typewritten copy of a personal account (Box 1.)
  - La Course de l'Amérique à la Victoire (America's Race to Victory), 1919
    - Text. One typewritten copy
    - Related material, including correspondence with Mr. Baker, U.S. Secretary of War; Mr. Churchill, Director of Military Intelligence; Marshal Foch, Commander in Chief of the Allied Armies; the French Ministry of War; a preface by General March, U.S. Army Chief of Staff
  - Statement on the military accomplishments of France and her allies during World War I, to be included in the third edition of the Handbook of the War prepared by the National Security League, 1918., One typewritten copy, including correspondence with the National Security League
  - Traité d'Assistance Mutuelle, Projet de (Project for a Treaty of Mutual Assistance), eventually published in 1924 (Box 2.)
    - Project presented by Edouard Jean Réquin, 1923
    - Project presented by Lord Robert Cécil, 1922-1923
    - Project presented by the League of Nations' Comité Special in London, and the Commission Temporaire in Paris, 1923
- Subject File, 1915-1940
  - Collaboration Franco-américaine (Franco-American Collaboration), 1917-1918 (Box 3.)
    - Memoranda and notes by Edouard Jean Réquin, from W.,D.C., including a list of the documents, established by him
      - 1917
      - 1918
    - Memoranda and notes by others
      - 1917
      - 1918
    - Reports by Edouard Jean Réquin (Box 4.)
      - May 1917-December 1917
      - January 1918-April 1918
      - May 1918-October 1918
    - Telegrams
      - Sent by Edouard Jean Réquin from W.,D.C., May 1917-February 1918
      - Sent by the French Ministry of War from Paris, May 1917-May 1918
  - Direction de la Guerre (Direction of the War), 1915-1917 - Memoranda and notes by Edouard Jean Réquin, including a list of the documents, established by him
  - Opérations de la IVe Armée du 6 au 25 juin 1940 (Operations of the 4th Army from June 6 to June 25, 1940), 1940 - Official report of the 4th Army's Staff, 3rd Bureau, August 2, 1940, including maps